Register of the Japan, Koshikan (Korea) records
Hoover Institution Archives
May 6 The outbreak of the Tonghak Rebellion. (Sporadic riots since autumn 1893.)
31 Chonju occupied by the Tonghaks.
June 1 Korean court asked for Chinese military assistance through Y[UNK]uan Shih-k'ai.
2 Japanese cabinet decided to send one brigade to Korea in case China sends troops to Korea.
3 Korea officially requested Chinese military assistance.
6 China notified Japan of sending troops to Korea.
7 Japan notified China of sending troops to Korea.
June 10 Japanese Minister Otori Keisuke returned to Seoul with a detachment of marines.
12 Chinese expeditionary forces landed at Asan.
14 Korean government demanded the withdrawal of Japanese troops from Korea.
16 Japanese brigade landed at Inchon. Japanese Foreign Minister Mutsu Munemitsu proposed to the Chinese Minister in Tokyo a joint plan for the suppression of the Tonghak Rebellion and for the implementation of reforms in Korea.
21 Chinese government rejected the Japanese proposal.
25 Upon the request of the Korean government, the American, British, French, and Russian Ministers in Seoul urged China and Japan to withdraw simultaneously their troops from Korea.
26 Japanese Minister to Korea Otori strongly urged the King to carry out internal reforms.
27 Special instructions from the Japanese Foreign Ministry to Minister Otori to prepare an appropriate pretext for the beginning of hostilities.
30 Russian Minister in Tokyo advised Japan to comply with the Korean demand for the withdrawal of Japanese troops from Korea and warned that otherwise Japan would assume grave responsibilities.
July 3 Otori presented to the Korean government a plan for administrative reform.
9 American Minister in Tokyo warned Japan not to reject the Korean demand for the withdrawal of Japanese troops from Korea.
12 U.S. Admiral S. Kerett arrived at Inchon.
20 Otori presented an ultimatum to the Korean government to abrogate Korea's tributary relationship to China.
23 The former Korean Regent (Taewongun) took over the government under Japanese protection. Kim Hong-jip became Prime Minister.
25 The former Regent demanded the withdrawal of Chinese troops from Korea. Japanese fleet clashed with the Chinese fleet near Inchon. Korea nullified all treaties with China.
26 The "Kap'o Reforms" by Prime Minister Kim Hong-jip.
28 The former Regent restored to the Regency and declared war on China (?).
28-29 Battle of Song'hwan and Asan. First Japanese victory.
31 Japan severed diplomatic relations with China.
Aug. 1 Japan declared war on China.
20 Korean-Japanese preliminary agreement for an alliance signed.
26 Korean-Japanese Offensive-Defensive Alliance signed by Minister Otori and Korean Foreign Minister Kim Yun-sik.
Sept. 1 Prince Saionji Kimmochi arrived at Seoul.
Oct. 15 Japanese Minister Inoue Kaoru arrived in Seoul.
Nov. 20 Minister Inoue presented demands to the Korean government (later known as "The Twenty Demands").
Dec. 17 Ousting of the Regent. Kim Hong-jip formed a "reform" cabinet. Pak Yong-hyo appointed Minister of Interior, So Kwang-pom the Minister of Justice, and Dr. Philip Jaisohn (So Chae-p'il) Government Advisor. Administrative reforms in Korea.
1895
Jan. 21 Additional administrative reforms in Korea. Pak Chong-yang became Prime Minister.
Mar. 30 Agreement for a loan of 3,000,000 yen signed between the Korean government and the Bank of Japan.
Apr. 17 The Treaty of Shimonoseki signed. China and Japan recognized the complete independence of Korea.
24 The Tonghak leader Chon Pong-jun executed.
May 14 Overthrow of the Kim Hong-jip Cabinet by the pro-Russian faction.
June 7-8 Pak Yong-hyo fled to Japan. Pak Chong-yang formed a pro-Russian cabinet.
Aug. 24 Kim Hong-jip reappointed Prime Minister.
Sept. 1 Japanese Minister Count Miura Goro arrived in Seoul.
Oct. 8 The "Ulmi Incident." Queen Min assassinated. The fall of the pro-Russian cabinet and the rise of a pro-Japanese faction under the Regent. Insurrection in Seoul.
13 Military reforms in Korea.
17 Japanese Minister Miura recalled to Japan and replaced by Komura Jutaro.
21 Inoue Kaoru dispatched to Korea as Special Envoy.
26 Count Miura arrested and brought to trial for conspiracy in Korea. Japanese government declared a policy of non-intervention in Korea.
Nov. 28 Attempted kidnapping of the King by the pro-Russian group under An Kyong-su and Yi Pom-jin.
Dec. Ibyong ("Righteous Army") uprising.
1896
Jan. 1 Western Calendar adopted in Korea.
Feb. 9 Russian Minister Weber arrived in Seoul accompanied by two hundred Russian sailors.
10-11 Yi Pom-jin conspiracy. The King and the Crown Prince fled to the Russian Legation. Pro-Japanese Prime Minister Kim Hong-jip arrested and executed. Kim Byong-si formed a new cabinet with Yi Wan-yong as Foreign Minister.
17 O Yun-jung assassinated.
Mar. 5 Japanese Prime Minister Ito Hirobumi arrived in Seoul.
29 American financier James R. Morse signed an agreement with the Korean government for the construction of a railroad between Seoul and Inchon.
Apr. 7 Dr. Philip Jaisohn (So Chae-p'il) founded Tong'nip Shinmun (The Independent News), a Korean-English bilingual newspaper in Seoul.
May 14 Russo-Japanese (Weber-Komura) agreement on Korea signed in Seoul.
16 Japanese Minister Komura urged the Korean King to return from the Russian Legation to the Palace.
21 Pak Yong-hyo fled to Japan.
June 3 Russo-Chinese (Li-Lobanov) Treaty; secret military alliance against Japan in case of the latter's attack on Russia, China or Korea signed in St. Petersburg.
9 Russo-Japanese (Lobanov-Yamagata) agreement on Korea signed in St. Petersburg.
July 3 French company Fives Lille obtained a concession for the construction of a railroad between Seoul and Iju.
16 Japanese Minister Hara Satoshi arrived in Seoul.
Aug. A Vladivostok merchant Bryner obtained from the Korean government a timber concession in the Yalu and Tumen river valleys. (This concession was purchased from Bryner by the Russian Ministry of Imperial Household through Matiunin and Neporozhniv in May 1898.)
Sept. 3 Japanese Minister Hara left Korea.
Oct. 5 The Council of State urged the King to return from the Russian Legation to the Palace.
24 Colonel Putiata and other Russian military personnel arrived in Korea.
Nov. 21 Construction of the Independence Arch and publication of Tong'nip Shinmun (The Independence News) by Tae Han Hyop'hoe.
1897
Feb. 20 The King left the Russian Legation, and took residence at the newly constructed Kyong'un (Toksu) Palace.
23 Russo-Korean agreement for the employment of 160 Russian military instructors.
24 Japanese Chargé d'Affaires Kato Masuo appointed Minister to Korea.
27 Japan protested against the Russo-Korean agreement for the employment of Russian military instructors in Korea.
Mar. 12 Japanese government informed the King of the secret provisions of the Russo-Japanese Agreement of 1896.
Aug. 17 Proclamation of the new reign name of Kwangmu.
Sept. A. de Speyer (Shpeer) replaced Weber as Russian Minister. Arrival of Russian financial adviser K. Alekseev, and Russian military instructors to Korea.
Oct. 11 The Kingdom of Choson became the Tae Han Empire. The King adopted an Imperial title.
12 Coronation of Emperor Kojong.
16 Signing of an agreement with Great Britain, United States, Japan, France, Russia, and Germany concerning the opening of Mokp'o and Chinnamp'o.
28 Korean-Japanese agreement for a loan of 1,000,000 yen for the construction of a railroad between Seoul and Inchon. (Later abrogated.)
Nov. Russian Minister Speyer succeeded in replacing the British financial adviser and Chief of Customs Brown by Alekseev. Approval of the Russo-Korean Bank charter.
4 Independence Club banquet incident.
Dec. 1 Russian fleet arrived at Inchon.
16 Japanese government protested against the appointment of Alekseev.
1898
Jan.-Mar. Anti-Russian agitation by the Independence Club, specifically against Russian financial adviser Alekseev and the Russian military instructors.
Jan. 2 Ex-Foreign Minister Kim Yun-sik banished to Chejudo Island.
15 Baron Roman Rosen, Russian Minister in Tokyo, proposed a Russo-Japanese convention on Korea to Japanese Foreign Minister Nishi Tokujiro.
Feb. Japan demanded the transfer of the financial advisership in Korea from Russia to Japan.
22 The death of the former Regent Taewongun.
Mar. Korean government dismissed Alekseev as financial adviser and Chief of Customs, and restored Brown to his former position after a strong protest by the British Minister in Seoul J. H. Jordan.
1 Russo-Korean Bank established in Seoul. (Closed shortly afterwards.)
Mar. 7 Russia demanded Korea's acceptance of Russian aid.
12 Korean government demanded the withdrawal of the Russian military mission from Korea.
19 Japanese proposal to Russia to exchange spheres of influence (Korea for Manchuria).
23 Withdrawal of Russian advisers and Russian military mission from Korea.
r. 12 Speyer resigned as Russian Minister to Korea; replaced by N. Matiunin.
25 Russo-Japanese (Rosen-Nishi) Agreement on Korea signed. Both parties pledged non-interference in the internal affairs of Korea.
July 11 The "Abdication Conspiracy." An Kyong-su fled to Japan.
28 Prince Heinrich of Prussia visited Korea.
Sept. Negotiations between James R. Morse and a Japanese firm for the sale of Seoul-Inchon railroad concession.
8 Korean-Japanese agreement for the construction of a railroad between Seoul and Pusan signed.
12 A pro-Russian Korean Kim Hong-yuk attempted to poison the Emperor and the Crown Prince.
14 Pak Yong-hyo returned to Korea.
Oct. 17- Nov.27 Clashes between members of Tong'nip Hyop'hoe (The Independence Club) and Hwangguk Hyop'hoe (The Imperial Association).
20 Manminhoe (The All People's Assembly) organized by the Independence Club.
Nov. 26 The Independence Club and the Imperial Association dissolved by Imperial decree.
1899
Jan. 12 Russian Minister to Korea Pavlov arrived.
Mar. 29 Count Henry Keyserling, a Russian, secured a whaling concession.
30 A British M.P. Pritchard-Morgan appointed Honorary Korean Consul-General in London.
May 26 The "Streetcar Incident" in Seoul. Rioting against the Korean American Electric Company.
June 2 Signing of foreign settlement regulations for Masan, Kunsan and Songjin.
July 8 Prince Heinrich of Prussia visited Korea.
Sept. 11 Korean-Chinese Commercial Treaty signed.
Nov. 14 Japanese Minister Hayashi Gonsuke arrived.
1900
Feb. 14 Granting of a whaling concession to Japan.
Mar. 8 William H. Stevens appointed Honorary Korean Consul-General in New York.
Mar. 18 Japanese Minister Hayashi protested against Korea's lease of land to Russia in Masan and demanded lease of land on Kojedo Island in Chin'hae Bay for Japan.
Mar. 30 Korean-Russian secret treaty for the lease of land in Masan.
May 17 An Kyong-su and others sentenced to death.
Summer Japanese Minister to Russia began negotiations for the revision of Russo-Japanese agreements on Korea of 1896 and 1898.
Oct. 3 Korean-Japanese Supplementary Fisheries Convention signed.
1901
Jan. 23 Japan refused to consider the Russian proposal for the neutralization of Korea until the withdrawal of Russian troops from Manchuria.
26 The Chinese Minister in Seoul protested the violation of Korean-Manchurian boundary by the Korean Army.
Mar. 23 Korean-Belgian Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation signed.
29 Russian warships arrived in Inchon Bay.
Apr. 17 Korean-French Postal Agreement signed.
20 Japanese Minister Hayashi demanded the rights for the construction of telegraph lines and submarine cables between Pusan and Masan. (Previously, Russia had obtained the right to construct telegraph lines between Seoul and Vladivostok.)
July 23 National Grain Law, prohibiting export of grain to Japan proclaimed.
Aug. 8 Japan protested against the Korean Grain Law.
Sept. 6 A loan contract for 500,000 yen signed between the First Bank of Tokyo (Daiichi Ginko) and the Korean government.
Oct. 8 Korea rejected a Russian request for telegraph line concessions.
Nov. 14 Italian Legation in Korea opened.
15 Grain laws repealed.
30 The meeting between Ito Hirobumi and Russian Foreign Minister Lamsdorf. Ito proposed that Russia recognize Korea to be in the Japanese sphere of influence.
Dec. 4 Ito presented to Rusian Foreign Minister Lamsdorf a draft of a Russo-Japanese agreement on Korea.
13 Lamsdorf proposed certain restrictions on Japanese activity in Korea (Russian agreement before Japan could dispatch troops to Korea, etc.).
23 Breakdown of Russo-Japanese negotiations.
31 Revision of Korean Customs Law.
1902
Jan. 11 Indictment of E. T. Bethell of the Korea Daily News.
30 Signing of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance. Great Britain recognized the independence of Korea and Japanese special interests there.
Feb. 26 Korean government rejected a French loan proposal.
Mar. 12 The French Minister in Seoul protested against the rejection of a French loan proposal.
23 Daiichi Ginko's one yen note recognized as legal tender in Korea.
Apr. 24 Construction began on a railroad between Seoul and Shin'iju.
May 17 Japanese-Korean agreement concerning the Japanese settlement at Masan.
20 Daiichi Ginko circulated demand drafts in Korea.
June 25 Anti-Japanese uprisings in the Cholla Provinces.
July 15 Korean-Danish Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation signed.
1903
Jan. 7 Korean government banned the circulation of Daiichi Ginko notes in Korea.
Feb. 3 The second ban on the circulation of Daiichi Ginko notes in Korea.
13 Korean government repealed the ban on the circulation of Daiichi Ginko notes in Korea.
16 Russian Chargé d'Affaires E. Stein requested the Korean government for a railroad concession between Seoul and Shin'iju.
17 The Belgian Consul requested mining concessions.
20 Korean government rejected the Russian request for a railroad concession between Seoul and Shin'iju.
25 Merger of the Seoul-Inchon and the Seoul-Pusan railroad companies.
Mar. 26 Bank of Korea charter issued.
Apr. 21 Russian troops occupied Yong'amp'o. Russian Timber Company established at Yong'amp'o.
June 10 Anti-Japanese riots.
July 3 Japanese Minister Hayashi Gonsuke strongly protested against the anti-Japanese riots.
20 Timber concession granted to a Russian company. Korean-Russian agreement on the lease of land in Yong'amp'o.
22 Korean government requested Japan to remove the telegraph lines between Seoul and Pusan.
Aug. 11 Japanese Minister Hayashi protested against Russian lease of land in Yong'amp'o.
19 Russian lease of land in Yong'amp'o cancelled.
21 New Russian proposal for the lease of land in Yong'amp'o.
26 Minister Hayashi protested against Russian lease of land in Yong'amp'o.
Oct. 3 Russian Minister in Tokyo Rosen reopened negotiations with Japanese Foreign Minister Komura.
17 Russia prohibited the entry of Japanese nationals into Yong'amp'o.
Nov. 1 Clash between Japanese and Russians at Inchon
17 Korean attempts to make Yong'amp'o an open port failed due to Russian objection.
1904
Jan. 9 Russian marines entered Seoul.
23 Korea declared neutrality in case of a war between Russia and Japan.
Feb. 6 Rosen-Komura negotiations broke down.
8 Russo-Japanese diplomatic relations severed. Japanese fleet sank three Russian warships in Inchon Bay.
9 Japanese expeditionary force entered Seoul.
10 Japan declared war on Russia.
11 Russian Minister Pavlov left Seoul.
23 Japanese-Korean Protocol signed by Japanese Minister Hayashi and Acting Foreign Minister Yi Chi-yong.
Mar. 3 Anti-Japanese riot in Seoul against the Protocol signed on Feb. 23.
10 Japanese-Korean agreement on the Seoul-Iju railroad signed.
17 Ito Hirobumi, Japanese Special Envoy to Korea arrived.
23 Korea granted to Japan additional fishery rights. Yong'amp'o became an open port to all foreigners.
Apr. 14 The Kyong'un Palace burned down by arsonists.
May 18 Korea abrogated all treaties with Russia.
July 23 10,000,000 yen Japanese loan to Korea.
Aug. Ilchin'hoe party organized under the leadership of Song Pyong-jun, Yun Shi-hyon, and Son Byong-hi. The party advocated the establishment of a Japanese protectorate over Korea.
20 Japanese-Korean Convention concerning the employment of Japanese advisers by the Korean government.
22 Japanese-Korean Treaty (first treaty of protection). Japan obtained partial control over Korean foreign relations and finances.
23 Korean Army reduced in force.
Sept. 6 Kankoku Kogyo Kaisha (Korean Industrial Company) established in Tokyo.
17 Mekada Tanetaro appointed Financial Adviser to the Korean government.
26 Japanese Minister in London Hayashi Tadasu secured British understanding of the Japanese takeover of Korean foreign affairs.
Oct. 17 Japanese Commander of the Korean Army General Hasegawa Yoshimichi arrived.
Nov. 1 Sections of the Seoul-Pusan Railroad opened.
Dec. 20 Upon Japanese recommendation, Durham White Stevens, an American, appointed by the Korean Foreign Office as Adviser.
1905
Jan. 25 Japanese Minister in Washington Takahira Kogoro approached President Roosevelt in connection with Japanese plans in Korea and Manchuria after the war.
29 The Seoul Office of Daiichi Ginko became the Central Bank of Korea.
Apr. 1 Japanese-Korean agreement on communications signed. Japan secured control over the Korean communications system.
May 25 Completion of the Seoul-Pusan Railroad.
June 6 The opening of the Masan Railroad.
July 2 Transfer of the Korean communications system to Japan completed.
29 Taft-Katsura Agreement. United States recognized Japanese suzerainty over Korea.
Aug. 13 Japanese-Korean agreement on coastal and inland navigation signed.
25 Renewal of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance. Great Britain recognized Korea to be exclusively within the Japanese sphere of influence.
31 British Chief of Korean Customs J. M. Brown resigned.
Sept. 5 Treaty of Portsmouth between Russia and Japan. Russia recognized Korea to be entirely in the Japanese sphere of influence.
Oct. 5 Japan took over Korean Customs Service.
Nov. 6 Yi Yong-gu and other Ilchin'hoe Party leaders advocated Japanese protectorate over Korea.
9 Special Envoy Ito Hirobumi arrived.
17 Signing of the Japanese-Korean Treaty (second treaty of protection). Establishment of Japanese protectorate over Korea. Japan took over Korea's foreign relations. A Japanese Resident-general to be appointed.
24 Withdrawal of the United States Legation in Korea.
25 American Chargé d'Affaires in Tokyo notified the Japanese government that all matters relating to Korea will be handled by the American Legation in Tokyo.
29 Former Ministers Min Yong-hwan, Cho Pyong-se and others committed suicide in protest against the second Japanese-Korean Treaty. Popular uprising in Korea.
Dec. 1 The opening of the Seoul-Shin'iju Railroad
20 Tokanfu (The Residency-General) established.
21 Ito Hirobumi appointed first Resident-General.
1906
Jan. 31 Japanese Legation and all consulates in Korea closed.
Feb. 1 Opening of the Residency-General.
7 All foreign legations in Seoul closed.
Mar. Founding of anti-japanese organizations and newspapers: So'u Hakhoe (North-west Learned Society); Cheguk Shinmun (Imperial News); Tae Han Maeil Shinbo (Korea Daily News) and the Korea Daily News by the Britisher Ernest T. Bethell; and Hanguk P'yong'non Chapchi (Corea Review) by the American missionary Homer B. Hulbert.
2 First Resident-General Ito Hirobumi arrived.
Apr. 17 Residency-General Peace Preservation Law proclaimed.
May 17 Popular uprisings in the Kyonggi, South Ch'ungch'ong, and North Cholla Provinces demanding the abrogation of the Japanese-Korean treaty of Nov. 17, 1905.
July 12 Japanese immigration law restricting the entry of Koreans into Japan passed.
Aug. 4 Russian Minister of Foreign Affaires Izvolsky instructed the Russian Minister in Tokyo to notify the Japanese government that the Russian representative in Seoul will henceforth deal with the Korean government only through the Japanese Resident-General.
7 Japanese Army in Korea organized.
Oct. 19 Japanese-Korean agreement on joint exploitation of timber resources in the Yalu and Tumen valleys.
Nov. 28 The establishment of Toyo Takushoku Kaisha (Oriental Development Company) in Tokyo with sphere of activity in Korea and Manchuria.
1907
20 Rumors about the dispatch of a secret Korean mission to the Second Hague Peace Conference by Emperor Kojong.
May-June Riots in South Cholla and the Ch'ungch'ong Provinces.
15 The emissaries of Emperor Kojong failed to gain admittance to the Hague Peace Conference.
July 2 General Conscription Law proclaimed.
3 Disturbances in Seoul after the arrival of the news of the failure of Emperor Kojong's secret mission to the Hague Peace Conference.
17 Pro-Japanese Cabinet ministers censored the Emperor for sending Korean delegates to the Hague Peace Conference.
19-20 The decree of abdication of Emperor Kojong. Popular uprising in Korea. Prime Minister Yi Wan-yong's residence mobbed and burned.
21 Pak Yong-hyo, Yi To-jae and others arrested for attempts to restore Emperor Kojong.
24 Japanese-Korean Treaty (The Third Treaty of Protection) signed by Ito Hiro-bumi and Yi Wan-yong. Establishment of effective Japanese control in Korea.
28 Emergency Security Law proclaimed.
30 Russo-Japanese Public and secret agreements signed in St. Petersburg. Russia recognized Korea to be entirely in the Japanese sphere of influence.
Aug. 1 Korean Army with the exception of the Palace Guard abolished. Riots in Seoul. Korean and Japanese troops clashed in Seoul.
Aug.-Sept. General anti-Japanese uprising in southern Korea. The strengthening of Japanese Army, gendarmerie, and police in Korea. By the end of September the major Ibyong forces were crushed, but guerrilla warfare continued.
2 Proclamation of the new reign name of Yung'hi. Maruyama Shigetoshi appointed Inspector-General of Korean police.
7 Emperor Sunjong's younger brother, Ubn, made Crown Prince.
10 Korean and Japanese troops clashed on Kanghwado Island.
20 Residency-General established a branch office in Yongjong, Kando (Chientao).
27 Coronation of Emperor Sunjong, the twenty-seventh ruler of the Yi Dynasty.
Sept. 3 Pak Yong-hyo exiled to Chejudo Island.
Oct. 10 Japanese Crown Prince (later Emperor Hirohito) left Tokyo for a visit to Korea.
29 Japanese-Korean protocol on the administration of Korean police by Japan.
Nov. 13 Emperor Sunjong moved from Kyong'un Palace to Ch'angdok Palace. Kyong'un Palace was renamed Toksu Palace and became residence of Yi T'aewang, the former Emperor Kojong.
18 Charter Oath of Emperor Sunjong.
19 Decree on internal reform proclaimed.
Dec. 5 Crown Prince Un, accompanied by Ito Hirobumi as guardian, left Seoul for study in Tokyo.
31 Appointment of Japanese advisers to Korean provincial governors.
1908
Mar. 20 Japanese loan contract for 19,680,000 yen without interest signed.
23 Durham White Stevens assassinated at the Oakland Railroad Station by two Koreans. (Died on March 25.)
26 Korean Privy Council adopted a resolution condemning the activity of Japanese Army in connection with the suppression of uprisings in Korea and demanded the removal of Japanese advisers from the Korean government. President and Vice-President of the Privy Council removed by the Japanese.
Oct. 31 Korean-Japanese fishery agreement.
Nov. 2 District courts established.
Dec. 28 Branch office of Toyo Takushoku Kaisha (Oriental Development Company) established in Seoul.
1909
Jan.-Feb. Emperor Sunjong toured Korea.
Feb. 13 New tax law proclaimed.
Mar. 6 Family Registration Law proclaimed. Population of Korea estimated to be almost thirteen million.
15 Japanese-Korean agreement on police matters relating to foreign residents in Korea.
June 14 Deputy Resident-General Sone Arasuke became Resident-General upon Ito's resignation.
July 6 Japanese cabinet decided on a policy of annexation of Korea.
12 Japanese-Korean memorandum on the transfer to Japan of judicial power and prison administration signed.
26 Japanese-Korean memorandum regarding the Central Bank of Korea.
31 The Ministry of War and the Officer's School abolished. The Palace Guard reorganized.